[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
there's one rule to stowa is when the
song starts getting really good
we gotta we gotta start um so
welcome to the stoa everyone my name is
peter limberg the steward of the stoa
and still has a place for us to go here
and
dialogue about what matters most at the
nice edge of this very moment
and i see a few new faces here if you
don't know what the
stoa is neither do i it's an emerging
mystery
some call it a digital campfire some
call it a communal podcast
and those really cool post rational meta
modern kids they're calling it a meta
sangha
which i don't know what it means but
maybe we'll find out one day um
so if our guest is not too scared by any
of that
i will introduce them now um we have
we're very lucky to have uh justin
weinberg with us
uh justin is an associate professor in
the department of philosophy at the
university of south carolina
and he also runs a popular philosophy
news discussion site called the daily
news
and i absolutely love this site this is
probably the best
like i used to uh be an academic
philosophy or
back in university days and i don't
really not plugged in that scene but
this is the site that i follow to kind
of get
up to date with that world so i highly
recommend it
and this the topic today is going to be
disagreeing well
uh i i reached out to justin wanted to
get him on for a while
and he proposed this topic which is
quite fitting for the stoa
because we were talking a lot about
reasoning while disagreeing well
i'm going to be launching a platonic
fight club here soon
i've been sitting on this like
innovative debate modality psychotech
for a while so i'm quite excited
so i'm i'm really happy to uh pick
justin's brain on this so how's it gonna
it's gonna work uh justin's gonna talk
for a bit
we're gonna have a few uh back and forth
and if you have any questions put your
questions in the chat box i will call on
you a mute yourself ask your question
suggestion
if you don't want this to be on youtube
because this will be on youtube i don't
want you to be on youtube just indicate
that and i'll read your question on
your behalf so that being said i think i
mentioned everything
uh justin how's it going today
it's going pretty well thanks very much
for having me peter uh it's nice to be
here it's a new experience for me
and hello to everyone who tuned in i
thought i'd just
start by saying a few words about my
general orientation
towards disagreement because it informs
my uh suggestions
for how we move forward
as a society and thinking about
disagreement
so i start off with a with a kind of
unconventional
view that when we're trying to think
about what the human
good is when we think about things that
typically
are candidates for the human good we
talk about things like happiness
we might talk about things like
knowledge i talk about things like
beauty i think that up there in the cat
that category of things up there is
conflict
or something like conflict there's some
good reasons to think that's the case
and that can go into all the details
about that
but that there we do seem to
get something quite valuable out of
conflict
we tend to enjoy conflict and
we learn from it however
right conflict isn't the only thing of
course
that's of value there are lots of other
things that might be of value
and in trying to figure out what kinds
of conflict we might want to engage in
we have to assess which forms of
conflict are compatible with the pursuit
of other kinds of things we value
right so you know we value conflict we
also value relaxation sometimes in
pleasure and
time with friends and music and all that
right
and so some forms of conflict are
completely incompatible
with the pursuit of those other goods
nuclear war
for example is a form of conflict it's
not a particularly great form of
conflict because it's incompatible with
most of the other things that we value
a watching a video
of two other people playing a video game
is also in some ways partaking in some
kind of
experience with a conflict but it's two
other people playing
a video game it's it's fairly trivial
it's not all that significant for most
of us
you know watching two other people play
a video game
uh what we need is uh a form of conflict
that's
compatible with the other things we care
about but something that
gives us what we need out of conflict
has to be important has to be meaningful
and so i think that a certain range of
conflicts
that we typically typically call moral
disagreement or political disagreement
hit that sweet spot
that is they provide us with the
good things that we need out of conflict
but are also
quite compatible with most of the things
that
we we value in life and so we should
think of
moral you know conflict is part of the
human good
and moral disagreement political
disagreement as especially
excellent forms of conflict
which means that these things are good
for us which means that
the typical orientation towards them
which is to think of disagreement as a
problem
as something to overcome or something
that we just have to
grapple with and live with like but it's
a huge problem that we're just never
going to get rid of right to think of it
negatively right i think that's a
mistake and i think it leads us to other
kinds of mistakes
rather if we see this agreement as
something that on balance is positive
we'll be able to figure out how to
appreciate it more
so this kind of positive feedback loop
there and
how i think to to to do it well do it
better
changing this mindset isn't a panacea
you know we're not going to solve
you know get rid of war we're not gonna
you know get to some kind of utopia
but i do think uh our lives will be
better if we have a
better attitude towards this thing that
is a part of our lives for better or
worse
and i think i'll just stop there as kind
of intro remarks
i i'm happy to say more about any of
that but i'll
leave peter to prompt me or the rest of
you sure
um so if you have any questions for
justin just throw them in the chats
um i could be wrong but i would say
most people would agree with that like
yeah this agreement is good i like
you know i think it's healthy to have
good disagreement um but
it's just lip service a lot of the times
and they don't do it well
um so would you agree with that
statement and um
the other question i have is how to
disagree well yeah
okay well so um you know i'm coming out
of
academic philosophy and if you look at
uh the course descriptions for say
a moral problems class you'll read the
course description and you'll see
something like you'll learn how to
reason well about these issues over
which we disagree so that we can
come to some kind of better agreement
about them right so make some kind of
progress
or if you look at what's going on in
political philosophy a lot of political
philosophy is dedicated to figuring out
how people who disagree can somehow come
to some kind of agreement like this
agreement
is this thought of this this we're not
perpetual problem we're never going to
get rid of it
so we have to do the second best thing
of accommodating it
right and then when it comes to you know
outside the realm of philosophy like us
in our everyday lives
uh i do think that the perception of
like what's going on online for example
all this disagreement's happening online
it's generally thought of in a negative
way
um and i think
when we step back and intellectually we
have in our histories
certain arguments say from john started
with others that that
argument is positive i think culturally
there is a negative balance towards it
something
to be avoided something to be resolved
something to get over
something that at best is just some
instrument to some point in time where
we're not doing this anymore or this is
the disagreement
so i i think maybe you know you like to
you you're
you're a former you know philosopher
you're
you're doing this thing where you're
you're disagreeing and talking to people
all the time so
of course they're going to be exceptions
to the general sense of things and i
could be wrong
but i think the general sense of things
is that it's fairly negative
there's a yeah there's a huge
confirmation bias i have so
that is true um uh yes
how to disagree well okay so
like that's a that's a huge question
this is something that that you
yourself have worked on a bit uh and and
have some interesting suggestions for
uh i i think it's important to
to understand that any kind of
cultural change is going to be taking a
long time
usually we can't expect
uh you know to institute some rule or
some policy and suddenly to have
long-standing forms of human interaction
change and it starts this thing
happens slowly over time and one of the
ways in which it starts slowly
is by talking about
values explicitly and then changing what
people care about slowly over time
it's it's uh maybe even educating people
starting from very young in different
ways so as to come to recognize
different things of value
so i i think that it's important to
recognize
the benefits of disagreement and be very
clear about them
making making the benefits of
disagreement clear to everyone
is one way of making it more attractive
and one way of getting people to see it
uh as something that they might want to
do well so there's
the kind of steps along the process so
how is disagreement good for us
right so so they're classic arguments as
i mentioned before from john stuart mill
about okay people disagree and they
learn from that disagreement their
epistemic benefits
like that um of course disagreement
makes the world a more interesting place
too
right people with different ideas coming
into conflict with one another the
conflict itself
it can be interesting and of course the
products of that kind of conflict
can be interesting and lots of cultural
products are the result
of conflict that's hidden somewhere
uh in their history i in doing some
research on this i learned
that tango for example the dance form
has its origin
in uh a kind of um
marching sort of physical conflict where
um the people who were
slaves in brazil at a certain time were
mocking the slave owners with a certain
kind of movement in parades
and that became the basis for tango so
uh
so even you know cultural goods can be
surprisingly
you know have their other origin in in
conflict
um i i have this idea of what i call
rival benefit which is the ways in which
people
who disagree with one another benefit
from each other in virtue of their
of their disagreement there are lots of
examples of this uh i think uh
i i talk about some in the art world but
uh sports fandom
is as a key example of this uh
it's much more fun to go to a game
and root for your team when the opposing
team's fans are there and also rooting
for theirs
you know you're getting something out of
that rivalry there that's kind of
pleasure that's
that's of course that's just kind of a
fun type of example but
i think there are many examples of rival
benefit and if we come to
explicate these share them talk about
them point them out
become familiar with them we might come
to see those who with whom we typically
disagree
as not this enemy necessarily
but as a much more complicated person
with whom we're in a relationship
right there's some things in which we
oppose one another but we also
benefit each other in some ways right of
course not all disagreements have that
characteristic but
but some do and so these are i don't
wanna i can talk for a really long time
i'm gonna stop
so it's less exciting just to hear me
talk i think and to have a conversation
but
um i do think that the first the first
steps income
in coming to a place where we disagree
better is coming to recognize
why we might want to keep disagreeing
and we have to see why it's good
the question is coming up now um it's
related to what i mentioned at the
opening
so i'm planning to launch a platonic
fight club here at the stoa so we get to
practice disagreeing together
um it's sort of like a container uh
and i think it would be really good to
have a course
i was thinking about this for a while
having a course on reasoning
where to discuss kind of like um dave
chomber's uh
distinction between verbal disputes
versus like factual disputes and his
method elimination
um and uh and i'm curious how much of
the nuts and bolts would need to be in
that
like do i talk about deductive reasoning
inductive reasoning validity you know
premises conclusions all that type of
stuff fallacies because
i find a lot of people especially the
store really intelligent
and they might not know you know this is
kind of like uh the analysis of
how to make of the argument structure
but they they argue anyways and they
reason well
so i'm curious how much do you think
that is needed in order to
disagree well a kind of an understanding
of the nuts and bolts of reasoning
it depends on on who we're trying to
improve and what their current level is
right what do we need
to make someone a better disagreer
right i do think that having
formal tools and understanding of how
arguments work what counts as a ballot
argument
uh how pieces of information
might not fit together the way they
would seem you know and certainly
mistakes in arguments i do often though
see
some formal knowledge wielded in kind of
dismissive and
unhelpful and unhelpful ways right you
give people a few tools
about logic give them a few fallacies
that they can now identify and then
they're just off to the races
you know getting at the formal features
of arguments in a way that
of course you know we want to pay
attention to that but can sometimes miss
the bars for the trees
right if we look at people's
dissatisfaction with public
discussion nowadays i don't think like
the top of the list
is you know people keep committing
you know they're affirming the
antecedent or they're you know
they're that i think fallacies are
really
the the main concern they're probably on
the list right people are reasoning
badly about each other's views
but i think people feel generally first
of all misunderstood
or partially understood right they're
like
it's not clear that those who are
disagreeing with them really understand
the view that they have um and so
i think mutual misunderstanding is a
worry
and that if we got better at
understanding what other people are up
to
and what they cared about that's one
thing another thing
understanding why if if you're
disagreeing over something controversial
it's controversial understanding why
he's controversial like this is
that that discussion is controversial is
often part of the controversy
around it and if you're discussing this
with someone who has a differing
view to you and you get the sense that
they just don't understand
what makes this such a big deal
then you're not going to get a lot out
of you
you might not feel like that argument is
worthwhile may not feel like your
opponent is even able to argue in good
faith
so uh i would i would focus
in addition to logical nuts and bolts
which i think are important
i would focus on trying to get into
the shoes of other people right the
perspective recognizing that when we
interact with people in certain formats
like in online format we're seeing a
sliver
of the whole person and understanding
that just as we ourselves are not this
sliver that we put online
where the sliver that is our view on
this particular topic
right um that uh you know we're there's
more to us
so getting people to somehow recognize
that aspect
of what our debates it's not
um the whole person there's a there's a
whole person back there with this view
that matters uh i think those elements
are really
crucial as well and are often overlooked
yeah what uh came to mind to circle back
to the the first part that he said
i think it was um robert tales and scott
aiken they call it weaponized metal
language how they take like
the tools of argumentation and people
abuse it and weaponize it
um i think ben burgess calls it like the
logic bros we're like just like throwing
fallacies at each other
um and so and then the second part of
what you said
uh like what comes to mind is like
intellectual humility applying to things
like principle
of uh charity is there any kind of
heuristics or principles you can tease
out in order to
come to understanding or in order to
come to with that disposition of
understanding
yeah well i think i think it's really
it's really challenging uh
and i'm not sure that there are a lot of
good shortcuts
right if you're i don't wanna i don't
wanna say that people shouldn't be
allowed to just uh you know have some
kind of
[ __ ] session about whatever topics
they want of course you know it's a free
country people can talk about whatever
they want
but if you're going to be engaging in a
relatively public discussion over
something
over some topic uh it pays to have done
your homework
to some extent on it right doing having
done your homework having
you know being aware of the relevant
details relevant facts especially those
that
not just inform your view but that
inform your
opponent's view i think are crucial to
debating to disagreeing well and so
um it's not it's not a heuristic right
it's not it's not like a rule of thumb
it's
it's the hard work of sometimes having
done your homework and then if not
having done your homework
and you sometimes have to to defer to
those who
seem to be in a better epistemic
position because maybe
this is what they're a specialist in or
maybe this is about
experiences that they've undergone that
you haven't right
so i i think
being aware of what you don't know and
being sensitive to that is a crucial
part of
disagreeing well um
so yeah so uh what again so when it
comes to like a handy set of like
shortcuts
how i guess there's always this one um
if uh if you're
really happy about
how the argument is going that should be
a danger sign to you
i think um like if you think if you
think you're doing really well
right and this is a this is a
disagreement
over a long-standing seemingly
intractable issue
and it looks like you're just completely
killing it here
that suggests that you're not doing
something right probably right
and so that should just be you know
maybe maybe you're not making any
mistakes maybe
you're just doing wonderful time maybe
your interlocutor has certain kinds of
failings
but i do think that that's sometimes uh
a good uh warning light
to be uncarved for right
so i'll pivot to the the chats in a
moment just uh one last question
um do you think deep disagreements
uh what robert foglin called deep
disagreements how
certain disagreements that cannot be
resolved through argumentation do you
think that's a thing
and if so how to respond to them
i i think lots of i think most uh
arguments and disagreements i i don't
think that we
should have uh hope that most of our
disagreements
are going to be resolved so
uh i certainly think that they're not
going to be
uh we're never going to run out okay
so i i don't wan i'm i don't want to be
seen as
advancing this skeptical view that will
never make progress on certain kinds of
questions over which we disagree
we certainly may but what we end up
finding out when we come to
some kind of agreement on on some
previously contentious issue
is that the issue is much more
complicated than we thought and
this dayton that we're yeah that gives
us
you know which we agree just gives us a
sense a pause a
pause by which we can then recognize all
the future questions that we have to
deal with i mean
in a way this is how philosophy makes
progress
right philosophy in a way never runs out
of questions
what we end up finding out is um even if
we
can answer some some question in some
way
doing so opens up a whole bunch of other
questions
and so philosophy progresses by
increasing the body of knowledge we have
about all the reasonable questions there
are to ask about
the things we don't know and i feel like
disagreement in a way is going to be
like that uh we may end up
resolving for a little while but but
there's a lot we don't know it's always
going to be things
further questions for us to disagree
over and furthermore
i think we're the kinds of beings who
for various reasons
like to engage in disagreement various
kinds
uh some forms of conflict and
unless we change our nature which we may
end up doing with technology or
something like that
and we're gonna have to scream it for a
while all right
very cool uh tim you are
up if you can unmute yourself and ask
your question
okay two would mute himself all right
there you go i guess that's me
yep all right hold on let me scroll to
my question
all right um are you familiar with the
stanovich's work on
cognitive decoupling or the ability to
block out context and
experiential knowledge john nurse wrote
an interesting piece on the sam harris
ezra klein debate where he broke down
his ideas
on why their discussion went so badly it
had a lot to do with their respective
approaches to the actual process of
debating
and it seems like there needs to be a
shared vision regarding regarding
how to go about having complicated
discussions and this isn't usually
practical no one will allow the other
person to
set the rules and engagement yet it
seems clear that those rules are
imperative
so that's an important observation uh
i'm not
all that familiar i'm familiar with this
term decoupling and i have a sense of of
what it refers to
and i agree with your point
that the parties to disagreement are
unlikely to each is not likely to allow
the other to set the terms of the debate
especially if they think that the terms
might
advantage one position
over another in a way that's unpaperable
to them
and i actually don't think that that's a
mistake
because the sense in which
we can distinguish between the
substantive matter
that we're debating over and
the formal features
like we're just going to talk about this
one thing okay right
like that's a move in the debate
that has substantive uh
implications for how the rest of the
disagreement will go
so i'm less convinced
that we can easily distinguish
between setting the terms of a debate in
some neutral way
and making
substantive moves right there's going to
be reasons to suspect that
taking certain things off the table
isolating certain variables
right is going to
have substantive implications for how
disagreement goes
but i i guess maybe if we can try to be
honest about what those are
that could be some progress but i don't
think we should pretend
to pretend towards neutrality
yeah i think i think in um what they
actually were debating about isn't
really super important but that
that concept of how uh one person might
have a very
um science-minded sort of
take a hypothesis and stick and try to
maintain a a narrow path to iso
you know to isolate it from all the
other dependent variables that could
exist just
you know as straight as an arrow let's
try to figure this out without talking
about a bunch of other things
and other people have a very rich
context oriented approach towards
discussing things and they they don't
they don't like to
try to really narrow down to one
specific aspect
and um it it seems
very difficult because uh to have that
discussion between those two different
types of people which i think are both
very common types of people
because those are your life experience
shapes how you're going to
have that type of discussion and um
yeah it was it was fascinating that i i
listened to the harris klein debate
and it was kind of a train wreck and i
didn't understand why until
um john nurse kind of talked about those
specific ways of looking
at how to even go about having the
debate so it was pretty fascinating to
me and
just made me think before i engage with
someone else
i need to think how is it that they are
engaging like what is their style of
engagement
and what can i do to not clash with that
style of engagement even if it's not the
way that i would like to do it and
that's
that's not an easy thing to do i don't
think
and and we might learn from
disagreements that derail
that that go badly right so if there's a
if
if there comes a point where you and
your interlocutor
thought that you were you thought you
were focusing on this one specific claim
and you pushed it to a certain level of
debate and then your interlocutor
can't proceed without bringing in these
other things
what are we learning right well one
conclusion is
my partner is a low decoupler they stink
at arguing right that i think that's
not probably the best conclusion to draw
maybe it's true but that shouldn't
probably be your first bet
the first step might be well maybe
there's these i these elements are much
more closely related
than i initially thought uh and let's
maybe we should explore that
so ways in which disagreements might go
badly from one point of view might be
seen as opportunities
to to learn about the issue because
um you know i guess not all
fails are um
things we can't look yeah our epistemic
fails
great thanks great key europe
[Music]
you may have answered this question in
the last bit of what you said
not all fails or epistemic fails but
i'll ask the question
anyways um because
i just didn't do my homework before
coming to the
session so can you please describe
what epistemic defeat means to you
i noticed that you published a post
about a research fellow
who wrote about agency rationality and
epistemic
defeat would love to hear your views on
this and how
to talk about it with the forms of
conflict that adds to understanding
thanks i'm afraid i'm going to
disappoint you
because so it's true that i posted about
some person who won a very large grant
for work on epistemic defeat but that
was that person's research project
it's not my research project so one of
the things i do at daily news is just
post news about what's happening in
philosophy
and when someone gets a million dollar
grant to do some philosophy that's news
so that's what happened um uh so i don't
have a particular
uh i think particularly interesting
conception
of epistemic defeat but but to go back
to that point about
not all fails or epistemic fails
i i was just mainly saying that look
this the disagreement might
come to an end right someone might get
angry even
right or the topic might get derailed in
a way that leaves the audience confused
uh and so the so the discussion
fails to proceed however right
uh we can learn just as you know when
there's a
when there's a car accident whether i
guess we're not with car accident but um
you know they're they're testing when
the engineers are testing products for
example
the product fails right or programmers
are
testing code and the program fails but
these are opportunities
for for learning i think the same thing
is true when
when disagreements go badly we this
things
disagreements may proceed in ways we
don't like other people might
proceed in ways we don't like maybe
you're more of a moderate person and and
you have
someone who's technically on your side
but they're just radically pushing super
hard in ways that you find objectionable
right
you know so there all sorts of stuff
might
might not proceed as you would like and
people might not behave
as as you would like but nonetheless
right
these are opportunities to assess
what we can learn from them not going
our way including
about ourselves and what don't i know
such that
all these people are happy for it to go
this way and i'm not
right if i don't understand why they're
happy then that's something i should
learn about
even if i don't end up agreeing that i
ought to be happy about it
so i didn't really answer your question
sorry but uh
at least there's some ruminations that
are in the vicinity
indeed thanks justin
nicole you're up
[Music]
hi um so my question is just the
difficulty that i have
experienced whenever i venture into a
conversation with somebody
um who like watches the news for example
quite consistently uh so my question is
it's difficult to disagree with someone
whose identity
is structured around their opinions
whether they're political
or religious etc and yet i think a lot
of people do have their
identity structured around their
opinions do you have any advice
or any suggestions for how does one
navigate
these kinds of conversations
yeah so that's a good observation
and it's a difficult question and i
think it leads
to a topic which i think should be part
of any discussion about how
disagreement is going to proceed which
is about
the context in which disagreement
happens
now uh right now so much of
our disagreement happens online right
in forums where you know we're sending
small snippets of text back and forth to
one another
and i think that that
is um a
situation that doesn't lend itself to
the most
understanding and as i said earlier like
when we're talking about what are the
kinds of things that we
want people to who are learning about
this agreement to learn
apart from say fallacies and reasoning
right uh
being able to understand there's a whole
person with whom you're
disagreeing i think is is an important
part of that
uh and and when we have
like twitter fights and stuff like that
going on
we're just we're just not getting
that that whole person but if you
have the opportunity like we don't right
now because it covered but
you know but you've probably had the
opportunity to have a conversation with
someone in person
with whom you disagree in a friendly
environment
maybe over a drink or something like
that
i i think that even when the person's
personality is wrapped up in a certain
ideology right they're just all about
this thing that
you can still try to put yourself in
their shoes
and still try to couch various points
you might have
in ways that
that they might recognize as
acknowledging from their point of view
what's important i would say let's step
back a little bit and maybe we need to
educate people not to
develop their personalities around their
ideas as much and and this is something
that i
i try to impart to my philosophy
students you know undergraduates
you know that in a in a class where we
deal with lots of controversial issues
they might come in the door with their
opinions
about things but it's much less
important that they be the one you know
much less important that they're the
ones who came in with the right answer
then they're the ones who leave with a
sense that they have a better justified
answer
right and that's the difference between
debate and philosophy and
or at least one of the differences
between debate and philosophy right with
the point is to be the one who came into
the room
with the right answer right the
philosophy it's coming out of the room
with a better answer
and um or at least a better better set
of questions
right uh and and so
i i try to tell my students you know if
you have a commitment let it be
commitment to what's true and don't wrap
your personality around an ideology
you'll go through life
worried that your idea some evidence is
going to overturn
your ideology and it'll turn you into a
jerk
and it'll be hard to talk to so
i totally get the problem that you're
dealing with like these
the people who've wrapped their
personality around
around an ideology and uh they're not my
favorite people to talk to
but i should probably take some of my
own advice and acknowledge that they
probably have something valuable to
contribute
and that we should try to engage in
context that allow us to
try to see more of their whole person
and
let them see more of our whole person
not just the presentations of our
ideology which is what happens in the
online context
sorry that was a big rambly but it
hopefully was something helpful
thank you sure we love rambling here at
the store just for the record
um evan uh you're up
hey so um i really like what you're
saying about disagreement and its role
as part of a healthy uh
interact way of interacting and i guess
the thing that i'm struggling with here
is uh you know the the [ __ ]
and the the frankfurt sense right
communication who's not really intended
to be true truth isn't the point of it
it seems like the public square
is uh to some degree poisoned or
infected by
[ __ ] and a lot of the examples of
debate that we see between
public intellectuals are are highly full
of
[ __ ] and that doesn't seem at least
to me to be a super healthy
way of conducting disagreement um so i'm
just curious what your thoughts are on
this phenomenon and if you have any
suggestions for how to
engage in disagreement in a way that's
less prone to
uh weaponized [ __ ] being slung
okay so yeah [ __ ] is a really
interesting subject
and like yeah so so [ __ ] has a very
negative connotation obviously
uh and in part i think justly deserved
right so [ __ ] in the sense that evan
is referring to
is speech that's made not because it's
true
right not in regard to the truth at all
but really just
uh to give the listener a certain kind
of impression of the speaker or to
get the listener to do or believe
something you know but
really not oriented towards the truth or
concerned with the truth it said with
disregard to the truth
um so what should we think about
[ __ ]
is [ __ ] the kind of thing that is
antithetical to good disagreement
i think the true answer is sometimes all
right
and i'm sure we can come up with lots of
examples in which
uh people's [ __ ] has
made a debate or disagreement or
discussion go badly
i i teach [ __ ] in one of my
undergrad classes
and i use as one of the key examples
this it's an old example now so i
probably have to update it but uh back
in when obama was president uh
senator john kyle got up on the floor of
the senate
and was complaining about the funding of
planned parenthood
and he says planned parenthood uh
they with a 97 90
of what they fund is abortions right
and you know stephen colbert made this
the focus of one of his segments and
colbert says well that's just
unbelievable in the sense that it's not
true
this true number is like three percent
uh of
planned parenthood's funding goes
towards abortion and as colbert puts it
kyle just rounded up to the nearest 90.
uh so but what was remarkable about this
story is that when he was called on it
what kyle said kyle released a press
release that said that was not intended
as a factual statement
so basically what he said was i was
bullshitting
right so now so so now we are at the
point right
where a member of the united states
legislature
is not only bullshitting but telling us
that he's bullshitting
and doing so because he knows that it
doesn't matter
right so that's where that does seem
highly problematic so i
totally get totally good on the other
hand
if there's something the last four years
have taught me is the importance of
[ __ ]
because look like any other person
you know we know that
politicians are full of it right even
the politicians we like
can be full of it all right and so
i used to be very cynical i'm still in
cynical you know about politicians and
when they speak and what they say
uh and then what we got
in the last four years is
um a failure of
a lack of [ __ ] basically is what we
have right we we've gotten
people to not even give lip service to
decorum to not even give lip service to
rule of law to not even give lip service
to uh equality and fairness
and our sense of public spiritedness and
as i mean i guess i'm comics on my rode
star here but
uh aziz ansari uh said
early on in the trump administration uh
that
that uh he was worried about the racists
who are in support of trump
and he's like you know he's like i know
there's always going to be racism
but you need it the problem is it's out
in the open you need to go back to
pretending you weren't racist
we didn't know how important it was for
you to pretend you weren't racist
but thank you for your service he says
please go back to pretending
and then the reason is that some forms
of [ __ ]
are are good right in a way that uh it's
a kind of cultural fake it till you make
it
kind of thing uh and we have to
sometimes be polite than we really think
is warranted
so that we get to cultural norms which
make it the case that people come to
adopt values that match up to what we
were
previously faking right so
i think bullshit's a mixed bag really uh
furthermore
right the kinds of [ __ ] that are
involved in in disagreements were like
where there's transfer there's sometimes
civility or the pretense of civility
is [ __ ] people suppose will fake
the norms of disability rather than
really feel them but that could be
useful too
right in a in a discussion so
uh i i we're not gonna i don't have a
recipe for getting rid of [ __ ]
but i think the picture of [ __ ] is
complicated sometimes good
useful helpful even for disagreement
certainly for other things
and sometimes awful and just the way you
recognize
a quick follow-up any ideas on how to
encourage
pro-social rather than anti-social
[ __ ] like in one's own personal
interactions or just on society scale
wherever you want to take that
yeah so i think if you carry yourself as
the kind of person who
doesn't mind being wrong
okay like if you if and if you can make
this known to others
then the one of the drivers for [ __ ]
which is this
need to defeat or win over you know
whoever is you're
talking with i think goes away right
because
if it's if it's no big deal i mean it's
in a way
it's it's modeling a kind of epistemic
humility kind of modeling
a um an aim at the truth
that i can i think undercut to some
extent
the motivation for for someone to
[ __ ] with you
uh so i mean we i think we need some
studies really to show which
you know this is just my sense of things
i'm i'm constantly out there from
front of a bunch of philosophers uh
saying things
that i know will probably be mistaken
and i admit it
and so i've tried to cultivate a public
personality for
being okay with being wrong uh hopefully
not
too wrong all the time but you know and
uh
and i think it helps when i'm engaging
with people one-on-one it helps
when i'm dealing with controversial
subjects that people feel like they can
trust me to try to at least understand
what they're up to
all right um steph you had a question
um yeah um sir i mean it's related to
the question of [ __ ] i feel like
online like we have this problem that um
you know on a place like twitter there's
no instinct and no push towards
us finding common ground like we like
we're drawn to um when we're talking
face-to-face
i'm wondering like if you've got any
thoughts on you know if
places like twitter were built from the
ground up what different kinds of ways
they might be able to be
built that would bring those best parts
of us into those
into those those discourse
spaces yeah so that's a really
interesting question and one of the
things that i was wondering about
just prior to this discussion was you
know is
is the problem that we're kind of in
this halfway spot
technologically where we're there's
there's
there's part of us that's online right
and and
it's this partialness which lends itself
to the
acrimonious bitterness this like sense
of futility sometimes a disagreement
that's happening
online in a way that is very different
from when a bunch of people get together
and have a discussion
uh in person right uh so maybe maybe the
solution is we need to move more of
ourselves online
maybe but i don't even know what that
would be i'm not a technofuturist or
something like that so i don't have a
grand vision
for for what that would look like where
if we're more robustly online
right i don't want to be the take the
letter solution and say well we just
shouldn't do this
right because so
um as far as making disagreement
go better in a context like twitter
i don't know i mean part of me thinks
forced timeouts would be a great idea
you know i mean or maybe let me reframe
like
what are the spaces online i mean this
is in my mind one of them but like what
are the spaces online
leaving twitter aside where you feel
like this kind of discourse has done the
best
okay so it's it's tough right so this is
this is something that i struggle with
uh so so i'm i run this website daily
news it's mainly for just
academic philosophers uh so the people
who comment on my blog
are philosophy professors philosophy
grad students and you know some other
people who
happen to have to be interested and so
you think these people
are training to be basically
professional disagreers they're going to
be great at it
and and i will say like they're better
than
average but still i think if you you
know it's my site so i'm gonna have a
you know i'll probably
have a better opinion of it than others
but but my critics like people who don't
like my site
will say that the comments are bad
comments are terrible
uh and it becomes and sometimes i agree
but like uh you know it's so even with
people who are well trained but okay
nonetheless i've tried
and i could try harder in different ways
but i've tried to
set out a mentality for
commenters and this is how i initially
did it it's a ra rather than set up some
you know a whole list of rules i said
this imagine that you are in a room
with people you like
and you're seated at a comfortable in a
comfortable chair and a beautiful table
with a beautiful view
with your favorite drink in front of you
and
you've come there to discuss
controversial issues
with people you like with along with a
kid
who you're teaching about how to talk
about you know this is how
you're with a kid who you want to model
good behavior for right
so you're comfortable your shoes are off
whatever you know
just put yourself in this mindset so i
just wanted people to relax
and just chill out and enjoy a
conversation
and i think that helps for like a month
or two or six months i don't know
but this blog's been around for six
years now and i think it's worn off to
some extent i have to go up some new
trick
right to get people in there but um
one of the things that's been nice about
kovitt of course is
being able to interact with a whole new
range of strangers
in a format where you can see their
faces and it's much harder to be snarky
in a context like this
right it's much harder to get like one
line off and
and think that you've triumphed in some
way right
and then everyone's thought like what a
jerk you know so
uh maybe like more technology right
along these lines more interactive
technology is the way to go
uh where we can again see more of the
person
and not insulate ourselves from each
other
thanks that's interesting all right uh
maybe
we can sneak in one or two more
questions
elf you had a question i believe
yep elf
hi justin uh my question is around
uh i'm trying to disagree well like two
things i've come across are having good
faith
if you don't have that that's obviously
a poison pill that's a big problem now
how to overcome that one
and then two like a disparity uh
in developmental psychology levels
depending on whatever model you want to
use but
the morals uh eq
the the cognitive complexity and like
how does someone that's metasystemic try
to deal with someone that's trying to
draw that linear line in the sand
so how can we disagree well especially
if most disagreements can't even be
resolved
right so i i do think that it's it's
the success of a disagreement is not
its resolution right it's not coming to
agreement
and i guess that's why i started with
the comments that i did
i uh look for practical purposes
sometimes we need to get on the same
page to do something like we need to
figure out which restaurant we're going
to do for dinner
so okay yeah so sometimes we do need to
agree but like
so i i shouldn't be too grandiose in my
proclamations about the point of
you know sometimes we do need to agree
uh
but um so
so that said like so you the question if
i answer your question correctly
you're dealing with someone who uh who's
just their way of being in the world is
is very different from your own like
their
their their goals of the conversation
are different their
capacity for engaging in it is is
different
um so okay so
yeah i'm not sure i have any like
well-formed thoughts about that except
it does put me in the mind of sometimes
when when you're a teacher
you have very different students uh
i teach at the state school there's a
huge range
of of students there with different
capacities different orientations
different backgrounds
different commitments different levels
of interest in the ideas and i have to
somehow
engage successfully with with them uh
and what what i find is is that that can
often be a learning experience for me i
mean i know how to deal with certain
kinds of people
and you know i do lots of different
people at this point in my life but but
along the way
and even to this day i'm still
encountering people who
i just don't understand how they're in
college for example or
i understand how they and not
necessarily because of a lack of skill
but like how did they make it given all
the other
stuff that was going on in their life
you know like sometimes that's the
explanation you know
so um
i think that you know you want to get
out of disagreement what you can
and maybe it's not going to be
convincing someone else to your side
maybe it's not going to even be
learning something substantively new but
maybe what will be is
learning how to present ideas that you
care about to someone who's
just so alien to you uh and how would
you
how would you go about doing that and
it's just practice at that i think
that's
you got to see what you can the value
you can take out of these kinds of
interactions
but even if it's completely i mean if
you can't find that then i would just
say
don't you know just say i am i'm going
to take today off
i i think you're right justin's practice
i was hoping you had some
insight porn for me but uh i think you
really got to know your [ __ ] to break it
down simplicity to communicate it and
then
also to meet them where they're at like
it's this extra step
so it's just extreme skill but yeah
thank you
i really like the phrase inside porn by
the way um
so christian uh has a question i'm going
to read it on his behalf
as a modern analog to the trickster who
breaks up norms to prevent calcification
and makes space for innovation does the
troll
have a healthy function in a society
where people can get completely absorbed
in their reality tunnels and conditioned
ideas feelings behaviors and could there
be a way to make trolling more
efficacious in this regard
rather than being done in a
mean-spirited way a quote-unquote sacred
troll
so i guess my my answer is it's yes
that's reluctantly in a way because as
someone who moderates a forum
i have to deal with trolls and they're
not
great to deal with but one of the things
that i've had
to recognize is that there
there are benefits to different forms
of conversational participation
they just they play different roles and
sometimes it's valuable to have those
roles
you have to in a way kind of do a cost
benefit analysis some forms of trolling
are just more destructive and annoying
than given the aims of the particular
forum
or the aims of the conversation that
you're engaged in
so i will say
yes to the big question controls be
useful yes
what does that tell us about any
specific troll in any particular context
not a whole lot we need to sort of do a
way the benefits and burdens
there but do so in an open-minded way i
think to recognize that
the trolling might be might be valuable
and just
you know keep it open as a possibility
even if you ultimately decide that it's
not
as for productive forms of trolling we
already i think we already have that
in existence it just doesn't appear to
us we might not call it when i call it
trolling because it
it steps up you know it's uh it's the
kind of person who
you know a bunch of people are agreeing
about whatever
uh some view and this person has access
to some article that has some empirical
information that completely undercuts
their position
and he's like ha ha boom right and
that's in a way
he's doing it to troll but he's also
doing it in a way that
actually is substantively informative
and so
low and behold we have some helpful
trolling
there um you know some of it might come
down to the moderators to encourage
the trolls to be more helpful in that
regard
was socrates a troll
no i don't think so um
you know part of part of the part of the
problem well so
so most of the time socrates is
interacting with people who wanted to
hang out with him
right not always right sometimes you
stop someone on the street they're
trying to settle away
but most of the time he's talking to
people who want to hang out with him and
that's one difference between the troll
and
socrates right but usually the troll is
not wanted
so all right
so we're approaching the end of the hour
i wanted to give you um
an opportunity to kind of any concluding
thoughts i know questions we're getting
from you from
all all corners which is which is what
this though is about
but yeah any kind of summarizing
thoughts well i
i think that you know for me uh
there's a lot for me to learn still
about this right so
one of the things we didn't get to talk
about today was some of the writing that
peter himself has done
on specific ways we might improve
conversational context and uh he
in fact has done a lot of detailed work
on the nature of various different kinds
of groups so i'm kind of sorry that we
didn't get to
talk more about your taxonomies and your
strategies there so maybe hopefully
since this is your form you get to do
that
uh at other times i will say like if i'm
just trying to get you know
one thing across uh it would well like
i'm not gonna be just one thing but
uh one of the things i try to teach my
students
is just how much more complicated all
the issues they care about
are how much more complicated they are
than they're presented to
uh presented by the media by politicians
by the authorities in their lives right
it's one of the great joys of philosophy
to leave students with more questions at
the end of the class about a subject
than they came in with right so they can
just see how complicated things are
and i think recognition of complication
is one kind of ingredient for better
disagreement
right for more honest disagreement for a
kind of epistemic modesty
that might just
uh cause us to be less
less oriented towards winning and more
oriented towards
understanding but that said sometimes
you know when people are arranged
towards winning and they push really
hard and it's annoying
it still can be something we learn from
so i think the other point is just
there's a lot of behavior we don't like
online
lots of people we don't like interacting
with ways in which disagreements go
badly
and to the best of our ability we should
try to see what we can learn from those
people and those experiences too
right yeah that's what kind of the stow
is in service towards is building a good
relationship with like
unknowingness in general and then
holding this complexity uh with while
not collapsing to one sort of memetic
driver or reality tunnel or whatever um
so that being said i'll make some
closing announcements but uh justin
thanks so much for coming to stella
today as a treat oh my pleasure
really nice conversation thank you thank
you um
so yeah uh we have a bunch of events
what's the next one i'm going to talk
about um
so at the website
yeah we have something called the
reflective structure dialogue with jill
de temple um
justin you might like interest are you
familiar with structured um
well how do you pronounce that
reflective structure dialogue
um i think i've heard of it but uh i
don't have any
content to go home with am i having
answers yeah i don't know much about it
either but apparently it's a cool
conversational uh modality uh catered
towards disagreements and then it's kind
of like a bunch of academics are using
it so that's
october 20th at 2 p.m eastern time you
can check that out it's part of the
communitas club
thing that we're having here um
and yeah so let's have a post sense
making session um
we'll turn off the recording uh this is
optional for you to stay just and you
can leave
at this point um and then we'll uh we'll
just jam
for for a little bit that being said
justin everyone thank you so much for
coming to stoa
talking with you all have a good night